I had an article that came through on a
news group that I follow and the article
was called bullies blind cat with laser
pen and this is in England
and I guess your four boys aged about 12
took turns to shine the laser into the
cat's eyes and then it goes on to
explain what they did but the the part
that I have highlighted here that I
wanted to ask him about and you
apparently answered it already but I
just want to clarify it it says the poor
cat was screaming and must have been in
appalling pain the vet told me the backs
of his eyes have been completely burned
out now
now would that cause pain when they say
the retina is burnt it's just burnt from
the energy
um
that type of I'm sort of at a loss to uh
to give you any direct or or correct
information there because I've never
looked into that but I can't tell you
that from a personal experience that
when I was performing lasers at Expo 86
in Vancouver I was lining up a 20 watt
laser in daylight
and my hand slipped on the mirror and
the beam crossed my eye very briefly and
I did suffer a small burn in the
peripheral vision area of the eye and
while
feel any pain immediately when it
happened I did have a headache and I did
have blurry vision for several hours
thereafter yeah I was just curious
because it was the laser pen that had
done this I I have difficulty believing
that because theoretically you'd have to
fix the target object very very uh
rigidly and you'd have to fix the laser
with a tripod or some other Mount very
rigidly if you've got a human holding it
in their hand no matter you can try this
yourself if you have a laser pointer
point it at a wall about 10 oh I know
you cannot hold the dot still it's
really very difficult so yeah simply
because just the actual movement of
blood in your hands and your muscles and
that natural trembles that occur in the
muscles will cause that dog to dance
around yeah because there's a lot of
times you see
the media loves to grab a hold of
something and I I just wasn't I'm
totally against any type of thing
against animals but a few months back
the show American Journal which is one
of those tabloid TV shows did a piece on
the dangers of lasers in airspace and
they arranged to have a 20 watt laser
set up outdoors and they got a
helicopter pilot to fly through it and
and give his Impressions and so on what
was rather interesting was that Patrick
Murphy the golden Aerospace issues
coordinator was there as well as Greg
makoff who is the chair of the Safety
Committee for the international laser
display Association and they observed
this important hated in it and what they
found very interesting was that first of
all the pilots actually found the laser
beam really amazing once when they knew
that they were going to be flying into
it and they had been forewarned of what
effects they could expect they didn't
have any difficulty with it they also
thought it was a very cool thing that
would make a great device for using in a
Glide path to show people coming in
where where the runway was now
interestingly enough American Journal
focused on the most sensationalistic and
negative aspects of the story and in
actual fact uh in true tabloid style the
uh
television shot that they showed of
glaring blinding light that was
impossible almost impossible to see
through was actually from the Xenon
Searchlight in nautilizer and
people who are interested in pursuing
this if you go to
www.pangle and
p-a-n-g-o-l-i-n.com and you go to the
American Journal TV page you can
download an MPEG file which has the
entire show and there's also a detailed
analysis of it there okay okay and you
also have a site which is a fantastic
site for lasers any information that
anyone would want is on this site we
want to tell the listeners a little bit
about your site we'll have a link for
that also
sure.laserfx.com is basically divided
into two areas the front stage or public
area is is aimed at the general public
and it has information on how laser
shows work uh
laser science projects and general
information about the industry and some
of the things that are going on the
newsletter conference Etc then we have
the backstage area which is open to the
public if people care to go there and it
is contains more detailed technical
information there's our newsletter is
available there are back issues of the
newsletter are available there technical
information technical papers archives of
Standards information a new section has
been added recently called pin outs
which lists the pin outs of some of the
more popular
boards that are used in laser displays
and there's a Resources directory there
too for people looking for products and
services in the industry did you put
this site together my goodness there's
about 10 Meg of material online you can
actually run it off our own server so
that way we can do updates as things
happen and it's a pretty big job takes
me a few hours every day just to keep up
on everything
well I want to encourage our listeners
to click on that link and go visit the
page after they listen to the interview
I did want to mention that the laser FX
98 conference is not a closed conference
there are only two laser industry
conferences in the world each year this
is like the light shows specifically one
of them is the international laser
display which will be taking place in
Amsterdam this fall but you must be a
member to attend our conference is open
to anyone
so people can come and just enjoy some
really great laser shows last year in
the competition we had today some shows
competing from Sweden Germany all over
the United States and Canada
uh the uh this year we have not only the
special audience scanning Workshop but
we also have Tim Walsh who is an
award-winning lasers from Texas who've
created quite a lot of really great
shows who's going to be doing a special
creative seminar and showing off some of
his work in discussing the creative
ideas behind it let's take an imaginary
person they've gotten a little bit
bankroll in the uh the savings account
and they'd like to get started with
laser light shows how would you
recommend they proceed with that well
the technology itself has actually
become cheaper in the last few years and
a lot of people start off by being laser
hobbyists and it's no more expensive
than any other hobby say owning a
motorcycle or a snowmobile they buy
themselves some equipment and start
experimenting with lasers and that can
take the basis of starting a very simple
system that uses wobbling mirrors to
make listen to type patterns with
information about that in the Hobby Zone
in the backstage there are now a number
of freeware and shareware Laser Graphics
programs available for download from the
net oh really yes and uh there's the
cost of scanning systems has dropped the
the devices that we use the
galvanometers that we use for making
laser images has dropped and the quality
has gone up against technology a number
of years ago introduced galvos that are
now doing 30 000 points
so now that you can take the older style
open loop galvos and using the
accelerators 124 technology you can
drive those at speeds high enough to
make uh proper quality reasonable
quality Graphics
in the old days a basic scanning system
would have set you back somewhere in the
neighborhood of two and a half to three
thousand US Dollars now you can put one
together for under a thousand US Dollars
and it's quite possible to spend less
than two thousand US Dollars and come up
with a functional right to graphic
system uh based on 100 milliwatt ear
cooled argon laser suitable for uh doing
basic light show type applications and
graphics and animations well that's
that's amazing I think it's across
without you yeah oh I'm sorry no but I
don't think the costs were that low no
they've gone right down that's
incredible the other uh development that
has come along in in recent years has
been the maturing of the white light
laser many years ago Krypton like this
with all line Optics were used to
produce multiple colors and uh in the
last few years a lot of research and
effort has gone into creating white
light lasers and there are even very
compact units out now for example laser
physics makes one that's only about 24
inches long and puts out 300 milliwatts
of white light coupling this with a
tcaom which is which is for
polychromatic acoustic optic modulator
you can now modulate multiple lines
simultaneously in an inline device so in
the old days we used to have to split
the laser beam up and send it through
different modulators and then recombine
it which was a very inefficient process
it took a lot of parts and work to do
now we have a simple inline Crystal that
can just be popped in front of the laser
beam driven with an appropriate
modulator and it's possible to get 16.7
million colors out of a system that has
8-bit resolution and some laser graphic
systems are now even controlling
multiple lines up to six lines that are
possible within trillions of colors so
the quality of the images that you're
seeing in laser shows has improved
drastically with the introduction of the
new scanning systems the color of
distance has improved with the
introduction of photopically balanced
white light lasers and the color control
of the image that you're seeing has
improved and you're even starting to see
now some rasterized images where people
have created images made of lines
because since you can control the colors
luckily you can use almost television
like images out of a laser obviously
this isn't you know full screen full
motion video it's still an animated
effect but uh nonetheless the
the advances in the technology have
brought great artistic advances to the
field and uh particularly in audience
scanning effects which we were
discussing earlier the the
sheets of light and cones and so on that
go through the audience now are no
longer limited to the typical seven
colors that you used to see but can have
lots of subtle shading and texture in
them and it's very beautiful to be
bathed in a sea of lasers I understand
that some of the laser light shows are
actually just coming on a truck leaving
the truck outside and feeding the laser
light into the facility using fiber
optics that that technology has been
around for a long time and I don't know
too many people who are doing that at
the moment but there are a couple of
people who have trucks that are
outfitted typically with higher power
yag lasers one of the nice things about
the frequency double the egg lasers is
that they're very power efficient
there's a system available that given a
220 volts
uh and a very minimal amount of water I
think it's about one gallon per minute
to too many psi will output 45 watts of
green light so this is almost perfect
for advertising because something like
that could be cooled with a recirculator
which is a tank radiator and fairness a
pump and radiator and fan assembly
and uh the uh outdoor applications for
that are really enormous because you can
mount the thing in a cube fan put in a
small scanning system and with a very
small generator and a small amount of
water you can be essentially a
self-contained laser advertising vehicle
as far as some of the newer patterns and
things that we see when we go to laser
light shows what are some of the latest
things that are being created
a lot of work has gone into 3D Graphics
platforms that that allow
to create images by means of a database
3D this is the same kind of 3D you see
on television the image is flat but the
rotating logo is calculated in such a
way that it appears to be
three-dimensional and it has perspective
and occlusion and so on and we're seeing
a lot of developments in that area it's
very very creative work from from people
lasers and projected laser images are a
limited medium when you compare them to
other mediums because the amount of
information we can display is fairly
small even given the new scanner
technology that we have the amount of
information we can display is in the
neighborhood of 15 to 1800 points of
information compared to the thousands
and thousands of pixels you have on a
television or a computer screen but the
difference they need the advantages and
disadvantages or the difference is that
artistically lasers produce a much more
three-dimensional image because of the
very high contrast ratio between the
image and the background and also
because of the very vibrant and Vivid
colors and there are also certain kinds
of artistic effects that you can get
with lasers that you just can't get any
other way and these are things like
Optical effects Lumias and abstracts
which are the strength of the medium the
early lasarium shows were based entirely
around that and made little or no use of
Graphics at all and now we have a lot of
shows where there's a lot of
representational stuff or you go to a
sports event and get to see a lot of
beams shooting around and players names
being written on the ice and that sort
of thing
and to me I'm I guess sort of an old
school laserist having been in the
business now for almost 24 years I
really enjoy a good abstract show where
I can just sit back and enjoy the
abstract patterns and effects which can
be generated in no other way than laser
the other thing about laser beam effects
and audience scanning is typically when
you do see these kinds of effects in
nightclubs in the US anyway they're all
over your head and there's no contact
between the audience and Malaysia in
other countries where International
standards are followed and audience
scanning is used the laser actually
reaches out and touches people and and
you'll be amazed when you go to a rave
in Canada and you see a feeling of light
being projected over the dances how many
people reach up and put their hands in
it and play with it it's just sort of a
natural impulse almost when people see
this that they want to touch it and play
with it and what's the what's the deal
here in the U.S it's difficult for me to
say because I'm not you know really
involved and I don't do shows in the
United States because of the burden of
paperwork but there are certainly
legitimate safety concerns it is
possible to damage people with damaged
people's Vision with the audience
scanning shows and I think that the
United States has heard on the side of
caution and perhaps gone a little
overboard on it in terms of changing it
I think uh until we until you in the
United States have a president or some
other high official who really loves
laser shows and I think he's really
likely to happen although the
international laser display people have
been working with your Regulators down
there but bureaucracy is one of those
things that's very difficult to change
and uh you know sort of the attitude
becomes well we've always done it this
way why should we do it any other way
are you still doing laser light shows on
your own oh yeah yeah quite regularly in
fact I'll be out this Friday doing one
in a high school okay great I do a lot
of high school dances Raves and parties
I invented the laser dance party uh 23
years ago and that is my favorite type
of show to do the corporate shows I
don't enjoy quite as much because there
you're often constrained in what you can
do by what the client's requirements are
the amount of time they have and how
many times they want to see their
product logo or the information whereas
at a rave or a party you've got a six or
eight hour time span in which you can
spend a lot of time playing with a lot
of different effects and I enjoy
performing the laser live rather than
sitting back can let the computer do the
show for me
what are some of the bigger names in
laser light shows do we have a
super group of laser light show people
um top three names laser light show
creators well it doesn't it doesn't
quite work that way because laserists
are the invisible stars behind the scene
in other words if you go to a concert
and you hear a great piece of music you
know the name of the guy who played it
or wrote it or sang it you go to a a
hockey game or a big sporting event or a
Fourth of July or a Canada Day show and
you see an amazing laser and fireworks
spectacle
who don't know who did that yeah the
person who spent hundreds of hours
designing and choreographing the Show
anime creating the animations for it
synchronizing and choreographing the
fireworks with the latest is some guy
out there on a scaffold back way back
where the public doesn't see them it's
not like you get to step into the
spotlight and bow yeah there are
exceptions to that I do a couple of
Tours each year in which I'm actually a
featured performer as part of a variety
show and I get to take a bow but most of
the time we're Anonymous as laserists
and we have to sort of get our enjoyment
from performing and our feedback from
hearing the crowds Roar and cheer and
whistle at a distance in terms of what
companies are the most well known
obviously the most famous company is the
one that started it all which is
laserium out of California
and then following on that the two
companies that are most active in
producing a lot of planetarium shows at
the moment are audio-visual Engineering
in Florida and Laser fantasy which are
located in the Seattle area so those are
sort of the companies that a lot of
people see but the industry has been
changing many years ago because of the
cost of the technology and you know the
support that was needed for it and when
you went on tour you virtually had to
take double everything because something
was bound to break uh big laser
companies with dozens of employees and
hundreds of uh jobs all the time were
the rule and in fact a lot of these
companies were structured where they had
artists and animators who never left the
shop simply animated and created shows
in the shop and then they had other
performing lasers who went out with the
equipment and did shows but that has
changed quite significantly in the last
10 years and now we're entering the age
of the small and medium-sized company
and even the one-person operation
technology has become more reliable it's
become more flexible as to what you can
do simpler and easier to use higher
quality output and cost less so now it's
possible for one person operation to uh
to serve a significant Market but as it
says in chapter two of laser FX the
light show handbook can you make can you
get rich doing live shows and the answer
is no nobody in this business has really
got spectacularly rich and I tend to
think that's because laserists are The
Starving Artists of the 90s just as
artists starved in frieden Garretts in
France for their for their art laserists
work very long hours under arduous
conditions with a lot of technical
difficulties and most of us do it not
because we want to get rich but because
we enjoy the art form and we enjoy
working with lasers you mentioned your
book do you want to tell us a little
about the book
um yeah uh I attend a lot of conferences
and I'm one of the people
that everything should be open and
people should tell each other about how
things are done when the industry first
started and I first got into it many
years ago everything was proprietary in
a trade secret nobody would tell you how
it was done and it took me months and
months and months of research to figure
out how to do the simplest thing which
is a linear effect you take a piece of
bumpy glass or plastic hold it in a
laser beam and rotate it slowly and it
makes this lovely one gas cloud type of
effect well nobody wanted to tell me how
that was done so I decided to start
telling people about how things were
done so anybody who called me or talked
to me I would give them that information
but it got to be a burden after a while
I found I was answering the same
questions over and over and I think this
was in the days before the world wide
web and FAQs became a big thing so I
decided to sit down and write a book
about it so I spent two years writing a
400 and some odd page book which is the
only detailed technical manual on laser
light shows available in the industry
the Bible I've heard it call back that's
what I've heard it called I don't call
it that myself
uh and so far the uh it's published in
small runs and made available through
our website and through people who come
to the laser conferences or who call us
and I've sold copies to people as far
away as uh Russia Korea Japan
Hong Kong China
Australia New Zealand all over North
America South America Chile so it's uh
it's done quite well considering that
it's not being backed by a major
publisher and there's about three or
four hundred copies in circulation now
great great
well I think we probably should call it
quits have we filled our time clock
we're approaching 26 Megs on the audio
file so well you're gonna have to do
some cutting and hacking yeah I don't
usually take too much out of a show
though okay okay well thank you very
much it's been an honor speaking with
you I thank you myself and the whole
talk listeners for coming on we're
basically holography related but we
touch on the lasers and laser light
shows a new area probably for a lot of
people that listen to this show but I
bet you there's a lot of people out
there doing Holograms that think I bet
you I could take this laser and do a
laser light show with it yeah okay
that's true well thanks very much for
having me on and I look forward to uh
doing this again sometime in the future
okay thank you very much